Yeah,
so it's כ"א *Kaf Aleph* with the...
up on the bottom of כ"א עמוד ב' *Kaf Aleph Amud Bet*
and we had just seen the first version of the story of
ילתא Yalta, *Yalta* who after showed her cloth to got an answer
that she did not like which enough was correct and then got
a revision answer. I should mention by the way that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* asks how did the second רב rav. *Rav* פסק psak
*Pasken* after the first one had, you're not supposed to override, and
it says that she that the first פסק psak *Psak* she got
that she was not what she was usually getting and that the
רב rav. *Rabbi* had some problems in his eyes, but תוספות *Tosafot*
interestingly and we'll get back to this, but I did want to
mention that תוספות *Tosafot* interestingly asks the question of how is she
allowed to go to a get a second פסק psak. *Psak*. Now
according to the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* answer, the answer is obvious that
she saw that it was a wrong פסק psak, *Psak*, but תוספות
*Tosafot*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't even ask the question and
תוספות *Tosafot* has a fascinating answer, if you look at the bottom
of תוספות *Tosafot* of כיום *Kolyoma* says גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ס' *Samech*
says ויש לומר דשלא היה השואל אלא לחכם והשואל ישאל כל מה
שירצה ומתוך כך נדקדק בדבר ופעמים שהראשון טועה ויתהדר הדבר לאורה *V'yesh
lomar d'shelo haya hashoel ela lachacham v'hashoel yishal kol mah sheyirtzeh umitoch
kach nedakdek badavar upe'amim sheharishon to'eh v'yit'hadar hadavar l'ora*. So it's fascinating
about תוספות's *Tosafot's* whole approach towards dialectic and multiple voices and arguing
things out that in a number of these גמרות *Gemarot* that talk
about you shouldn't override and you shouldn't be asking around for different
שאלות shailos *She'elot*, תוספות *Tosafot* presents a counter voice about the importance
that the more voices that you have and the more discussion that
you have leads to greater truth. So it's quite interesting that even
though the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you're not supposed to ask again,
תוספות *Tosafot* says well maybe it only means the other person shouldn't
override the פסק psak *Psak*, but really you should always be asking
around in order to get closer to the truth. So I really
felt it was important to read that תוספות *Tosafot* because it's true
certainly even in the theoretical level. Even if after you've got a
פסק psak *Psak* you're not supposed to shop around and that פסק
psak. *Psak* is binding to you, but certainly doesn't mean that but
the basic approach of seeking out and hearing other opinions is certainly
central to the whole תוספות *Tosafot* approach. So now we go back.
Right, first of all you'll know for the future and second of
all, and תוספות *Tosafot* says this like elsewhere, they'll argue, they'll talk
to the person you got the פסק psak *Psak* from and maybe
they'll convince him to reverse his פסק *Psak*. And according to תוספות
*Tosafot* that's a very healthy process. So what? Because איכא *Ika*. Okay,
that's a question we'll talk about. Let's continue in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, hold on, where are we?
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* ס"ה *Samech Heh*. איבעיא להו *Ibaia Lehu*: כזה טיהר
לי פלוני חכם מהו *K'zeh teher li ploni chacham mahu*? Right at
the line on the top of the תוספות הראש *Tosafot HaRosh*. איבעיא
להו *Ibaia Lehu*. So they raise a question. כזה טיהר לי פלוני
חכם מהו *K'zeh teher li ploni chacham mahu*? If a presumably a
woman says look, somebody shows her a מראה *Mareh* and she says
I had a מראה *Mareh* just like this, I had a stain
just like this, and this רב *Rav* פסק *Paskened* for me that
it was okay. Is that okay? Does that work as a פסק
*Psak*? So let's see. Now I should say a lot of this
is going to be the next this discussion is about women פסקנינג
paskening *Paskening* for themselves and for others, but the important thing to
underscore here is that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never somehow raises the
problem or the concern that let's say it's a woman not a
man. Maybe you could say that's implicit, but my understanding and the
understanding of all of the ראשונים Rishonim, *Rishonim* here is that is
that the concern here is by somebody that just doesn't have expertise,
which was certainly the whole discussion above was the degree of expertise
that was needed. So what happens if somebody who a doctor, let's
take this example, you had a certain symptom and a doctor told
you what to do, and then your friend has the same symptom,
should you be telling them what the doctor told you or should
they be going to the doctor him or herself? So let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* answer to that is. So it says
איבעיא *Ibaia*. So כזה *K'zeh*... מהו *Mahu*, what's ההלכה *HaHalacha*? תא שמע
Ta shema, *Ta Shma*, come here. נאמנת אשה לומר כזה ראיתי ואיבדתיו
*Ne'emenet ishah lomar kaze ra'iti v'ibadtiv*. Look, we have a ברייתא baraita
*Baraisa* that says a woman can say look, she doesn't have the
בדיקה bedika *Bedikah* cloth, but she can say to the רב *Rav*,
it
was just like this stain over here. I lost the cloth, but
it was just like this other stain. And then the רב *Rav*
can פסק *Pasken* based on the other stain,
even though it's not the stain that she actually just had. see
that she can be, that you know that you can trust somebody's
report. So גמרא Gemara says, "No, שאני התם דליכא לקמיה." shani hasam
d'leika l'kamei. That's different, the cloth isn't there. So, a, we have
no other choice, as opposed to the first scenario that there's always
another choice, go to an expert, go to
the rabbi. And b, also, which I would
say is also equally if not more important, is that there's a
difference between reporting the evidence and reporting a decision. You know, because
it's always a question that somebody who's not an expert doesn't exactly
know which factors were critical in the decision process. So to just
say it looked like this, that's just reporting the facts, as opposed
to our question which is essentially making a ruling based on what
you heard from somebody else. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. תא שמע, come in here. ילתא, Yalta now we bring up
ילתא Yalta case again. ילתא אייתי דמא לקמיה דרבה בר בר חנה.
Yalta ayisay dama l'kamei d'Rabbah bar bar Chana. ילתא Yalta brought her
stain, her blood in front of רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah bar
bar Chana, וטמי ליה, v'tamei lei, and he said it was טמא.
tamei. Then לקמיה דרבי יצחק בריה דרב יהודה, l'kamei d'Rabbi Yitzchak brei
d'Rav Yehudah, then in front of יצחק בריה דרב יהודה, Yitzchak brei
d'Rav Yehudah, ודכי ליה, v'dachi lei, and he said that it was
טהור, tahor, that it was fine. So the גמרא Gemara says, והיכי
עביד הכי? v'heichi avid hachi? This is again just repeating what we
said yesterday because once we reframe the case, it'll allow us to
ask our question. How could he have done this? והתניא חכם שטימא
אין חברו רשאי לטהר V'hatanya chacham shetima ein chaveiro rashai letaher etc.
Wait, excuse me, I said it wrong again. Not how could she
do this, how could רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah bar bar Chana,
excuse me, how could רבי יצחק בריה דרב יהודה Rabbi Yitzchak brei
d'Rav Yehudah override the ruling of רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar
bar Chana once there's a ruling that it's טמא? tamei? The colleague
cannot override it and say טהור. tahor. ומשנינן, u'mashniinan, and the way
we answer that yesterday was we said מעיקרא הוה מטמי ליה, me'ikara
hava matmei lei, that he actually, רבי יצחק בריה דרב יהודה Rabbi
Yitzchak brei d'Rav Yehudah was actually, you know, out of respect for
the first ruling, going to say that it was טמא. tamei. כיון
דאמרה ליה, keivan d'amrah lei, but then she said to him, דכל
יומא מדכי לי כהאי גוונא, d'chol yoma madki li k'hai gavna, that
really, רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana used to tell
me that that was okay, exactly these types of things. והאידנא דחש
בעיניה, v'haidna d'chash b'eineih, and it's just today that he had an
eye problem. So ודכי ליה, v'dachi lei, he said it was טהור.
tahor. אלמא, almah, you see, מהימנא, mehemnah, she's believed. Because notice, she's
not just reporting on the facts. She's not just saying, oh yeah,
it looked just like this. He knows what it looks like, he's
looking at it. She's reporting on the ruling, that he normally would
rule for me that this was okay. And to say that means
that we can trust her not just what things looked like, but
to understand what were the relevant parameters and that it'd be relevant
and that he could be trusted to say that this is the
type of thing that he would say okay. So by virtue of
that, she could also פסקן pasken for other people based on what
she has heard and based on her experience. That seems to be
a pretty good proof. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלמא מהימנא? almah
mehemnah? And the גמרא Gemara says, no, רבי יצחק בר יהודה גמרא
סמיך. Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yehudah gemara samich. רבי יצחק בר יהודה, Rabbi
Yitzchak bar Yehudah, he knew what the פסק was. He was basing
himself on his own expertise. He knew what the פסק was, he
just didn't want to overrule the previous פסק. So once he heard
that he had an opening to overrule the previous פסק, that it
was a mistake, then he פסקן, paskened, but he wasn't פסקן paskening
because he was parroting back what he said, he was פסקן paskening
because he knew for himself. And the גמרא Gemara ends without a
clear conclusion about this. And again what I want to reiterate is
that nobody says, not in the גמרא Gemara and not in the
ראשונים, that somehow it's an issue about a woman being trusted. It's
really a question here about not having training and expertise but being
able to, you know, assume that what you've seen, how people have
ruled for you, you can understand, you know, those parameters and therefore
pass that on without specific training in the field itself. And certainly
the first phenomena of יועצת הלכה, Yoetzet Halacha, this is like a
non-issue if you yourself are expertly trained, it's a non-issue. And of
course I have to say something also about the issue about Michael's
question about why ילתא Yalta went and asked a פסק if she
could have ruled for herself, and if she knew and if she
was able to report. So a, one part of that answers what
the גמרא Gemara is implying, maybe she wasn't expert enough to rule
for herself, but she was expert enough certainly to correct a mistaken
ruling or to suggest that it was a mistaken ruling. But there's
also a reality of, again, here dealing with a society in which
the male rabbis are the ones with the authority and how do
you sort of operate within those controls or within those parameters. And
it reminds me of, I know that there was a particular case
personally about a rabbi of a community, and I'm sure this happens
all over, you call him up and he wasn't around and his
wife would answer the phone and you'd say, look, I have to
ask a שאלה, shaila, this, this and this. She says, look, the
rabbi isn't available, but if he were around, here's what he would
tell you. And then everyone would just go ahead and do it.
So there's sort of ways of handling that situation without challenging the
rabbinic authority, which seems to be part of the message of the
ילתא Yalta case. But in the end, it's really a question, would
you tell your friend what the doctor prescribed for you? you when
you had similar conditions? Or obviously, you don't always necessarily know all
of the relevant parameters, and that seems to really be the question
that the גמרא Gemara, is asking. Okay, so the ילתא Yalta story?
No, because before it was just telling the ילתא Yalta story, you
know, to relate the story, now it's using it as evidence that
you can trust somebody to פסקן pasken for him or herself based
on what they've heard from a, you know, from an expert, you
know, what they've heard from a רב. פסקנינג paskening for herself regularly.
Right. So that, I mean, that's a good point too, you know,
why didn't it bring the opposite evidence? The fact that, the fact
that he was going, she was still going, rather than, you know,
that's exactly the point. So part, so according to the answer the
גמרא, Gemara it works out well, you know, she couldn't rule for
herself, she didn't have the necessary expertise. According to the הוה אמינא,
Havah Aminah, I would just sort of say that, you know, again
sort of like the whole theme until now that, especially in general,
the concept of sort of, you know, respecting the rabbinic authority and
particularly here, there seems to be a particular emphasis about that in
this area about ruling on bloodstains, you know, how that sort of
is symbolic of rabbinic authority, but it's a good, it's a good
point that the גמרא Gemara. doesn't try to sort of raise that
question, why was she going? Well, I would say that she tried
to, yes, but you know, it's always a question if you're dealing
with, you know, sort of as the, the power class, how do
you, you know, I mean she wasn't like blatantly disrespecting it, she
was finding ways to... she challenged it, but, yeah, but challenging it
in a, you know, it's always tricky. Yes, I understand, I'm agreeing
with you, but I think, but the point is, it's challenging, you
know, the authority, and at the same time not sort of blatantly
showing yourself to be a rebel and disrespect... you know, and disrespect.
I think that was the whole dance she was playing there, and
I think that's true about the other stories of ילתא as well.
So we're not disagreeing here, you know, the question is how did
she successfully challenge rabbinic authority? That's, that's the issue. Focus. Yeah, yeah,
so, yeah, a lot of, a lot of פוסקים poskim say yes,
and there's a whole question why can't you override. So you don't
override something a colleague says out of just respect, but if that
were true then if they said you can't, you can't override to
be strict unless, you know, the other person is really making a
mistake, or maybe there's some sense that once you get a פסק
it creates some binding nature to it and that, but you know,
and sort of, so פסקנינג that something is אסור assur the same
way you could make something forbidden on yourself, you know, maybe that
creates a certain reality of איסור issur that then cannot be rescinded.
So there's interesting discussions around that, but that's not for now. Okay,
so let's, and I do want to end this discussion by reminding
us that there was the ברייתא baraita earlier about a certain neighborhood
or a, I forget, גמרא Gemara ברייתא Beraita, that a certain neighborhood
that all the women would bring their, you know, their מראות maras
to a certain woman, a deaf woman actually, who would פסקן pasken
for them. So there's no question about, with the necessary expertise, obviously,
you know, somebody can פסקן pasken even, you know, even not a
רב. So now let's, now the גמרא Gemara. continues. רבי, Rabbi, we're
going to end up with this discussion about looking at the stains.
רבי ראה דם בלילה. Rabbi raah dam balaylah. Now, here, you know,
the question was raised before about daylight and sufficient light at night
and as I've already pointed out that candlelight not only is not
a lot of light but it also has more red in it.
So here though, you are, if you need to look at it
at night under candlelight but it's not advised. So it says רבי
ראה דם בלילה, Rabbi raah dam balaylah, so רבי Rabbi saw some
blood at night, וטימא, v'timei, and he said it was טמא. tamei.
ראה ביום וטיהר, raah bayom v'tihar, then he looked at it again
at the day and he saw that it wasn't a problematic color,
maybe again the light was better, and so he said it was
טהור. tahor. המתן שעה אחת, hamten shaah achat, so he waited an
hour, חזר וטימא, chazar v'timei, and then he said, oh, you know
what, better say טמא. tamei. This might remind you of the earlier
גמרא Gemara, about רבי Rabbi where he also ruled like something and
then like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and then he wanted to reverse
himself. So it's actually quite fascinating about רבי Rabbi always sort of
reflecting and questioning his פסק. Anyway, so then he went back to
his original פסק and said it was טמא. tamei. And then he
said אמר אוי לי שמא טעיתי, amar oy li shema taiti, he
said woe to me, maybe I've made a mistake. So the גמרא
says שמא טעיתי, shema taiti, maybe he made a mistake? ודאי טעית,
vadai taita, you definitely made a mistake. Why? So the גמרא understands
that, that, you know, that his first ruling at night when he
said טמא tamei was sort of tentative since you're not supposed to
look at it at night and it might be look redder, it
was tentative. So when he saw it in the day he had
a clear, he saw it well, he saw it well and he
saw that it was טהור, tahor, and that's when he should have
stuck with that ruling and to go back to what he said
last night, that's a mistake. What you saw last night you can't
rely on. So how do you know that? ודאי טעית דתניא דתנו
בברייתא לא יאמר חכם אלו היה לך היה ודאי טמא, vadai taita
detanya detanu babaraita lo yomar chacham ilu haya lach haya vadai tamei,
he shouldn't say, oh... No, if I had seen it when it
was fresh, when it was moist, then it probably would have been
טמא. tamei. Don't worry about what you can't see. אלא אומר ela
omer אין לו לדיין אלא מה שעיניו רואות, ein lo l'dayan ela
mah she'einav ro'os, that the judge only has what his eyes see.
It's actually quite interesting because normally that word what your eyes see
is metaphorical, you know, you only have what you know the evidence
that's in front of you, but here literally what you're looking at
right now, that's what you have to rule on, not what you
can't see, not what it might have been last night. And we're
assuming that what it was last night's ruling was tentative and really
is immaterial. So don't worry about oh no maybe last night it
really was, you know, not good and I wasn't sure. You go
by when you're able to make a real sound judgment, you go
by what you saw today. So why did he say maybe he
made a mistake by going back and saying טמא? tamei? So the
גמרא says where were we... אלא אמר ela amar מעיקרא אחזוקי בטמא.
me'ikara achzukei b'tamei. No, originally he didn't have a tentative ruling. Originally
he said it was definitely טמא tamei at night. Okay so then
why did he reverse himself in the morning? If it wasn't tentative,
how did he allow himself to reverse himself in the morning? This
is why the גמרא assumed it was tentative. וכיון דחזא דצפרא אישתני,
u'keivan d'chaza d'tzafra ishtani, when he saw in the morning he didn't
see it better, it actually seemed to him that it had changed
colors in the morning. אמר ודאי טהור הוא amar vadai tahor hu
ובליליא הוא דלא חזאי שפיר, u'v'leilya hu d'lo chazai shapir, I'm sorry
I misread that. In the morning he saw it was different, I'm
sorry it didn't change colors, that's coming up. He saw it was
different than it looked last night. He said you know what, actually
I ruled wrong last night.
At first he said he thought he knew what he was saying
last night,
then he saw in the morning and it made him realize that
maybe he didn't see it well enough last night and that's what
caused him to reverse. וכיון דחזא דהדר אישתני, u'keivan d'chaza d'hadar ishtani,
then he saw it later it changed colors again and that's a
new piece of information we haven't said until now, that what caused
the second reversal, what he saw again that it looked different. So
then he said... וכיון דחזא דהדר אישתני u'keivan d'chaza d'hadar ishtani אמר
ודאי טמא הוא, amar vadai tamei hu, you know what, really it
was always טמא tamei last night ומפחח הוא דקא מפחח ואזיל, u'mifachach
hu d'ka mifachach v'azil, this is just something that's constantly changing colors.
So basically what it says is it's changing colors. Meaning the reason
it looked different in the morning was not that I mis-saw it
last night. The reason it looked different in the morning, now that
I see that in the morning it looked one way and then
later the same day, even in daylight, it looked different, I see
that this thing is constantly changing colors. So I'm going to go
back to my first ruling. You know, it's like they say, you
know, the last time I thought I made a mistake, I was
wrong. So he said so you know, so he says you know
I thought so actually when I thought that I made a mistake,
I really didn't make a mistake. It wasn't that I didn't see
it well enough last night, it was that it's changing colors and
therefore I'm going to go back to my first ruling. So from
here implicitly we see a couple of very important things. We see
number one you shouldn't be ruling at night, it's likely that you're
not seeing it well. And even when he thought he saw it
well he was prepared to reverse himself, and maybe in general you
should only give a tentative ruling at night, but you should certainly
reverse yourself the next morning if it seems like now you're seeing
it in better light. And so that's number one, and number two
is the idea that you know you go by what you're seeing
right now and what you're seeing when you're seeing it well and
you don't worry about what it was at an earlier stage. This
is very important because women will often do a בדיקה bedika. and
it'll you know something looks red and looks not good. And by
the time they get around to bringing it to the rabbi it's
dried and it looks totally fine, and you don't have to worry
about what it was when you're not seeing it. You only worry
about what it was from what you're seeing and what's brought in
front of you. Of course if the woman says it was definitely
not good, you know, then that's it, end of story, then she's
essentially ruling for herself. But if there was any doubt, it just
totally goes by what the rabbi is seeing. So these are very
critical about you know about not looking at night ideally and being
able to override what you said at night if you know because
it's not good because it's never as seen it in full light.
And at the same time also not worrying about what might have
been before you saw it. Why did he look at it a
third time? I don't know, maybe because he still obviously had some
doubts. Clearly Rabbi was constantly revising, you know, and rethinking his פסקים,
psakim, which I think is a good quality. Okay so now the
גמרא says like this... what... no not at all... right... right but
he obviously had some doubts... exactly, exactly. So now the גמרא says
like this: רבי בדיק לאור הנר, Rabbi badik l'or haner, Rabbi would
check by candlelight. That was pretty obvious from the previous discussion. רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי בדיק ביום המעונן בין העמודים, Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi
badik b'yom hame'unan bein ha'amudim, he would check on a cloudy day
between the pillars. So it was in the sunlight but in indirect
sunlight between shade. So now because Rabbi checked by candlelight and that's
sort of like not ideal, he even checked by candlelight. רש"י Rashi
wants to read this also you can even check by indirect sunlight
but actually... The practice is to check דוקא davka with indirect sunlight.
Direct sunlight also does not give you a clear, does not give
you a good light. I mean it gives you a lot of
light but not accurate light in order with which to see it
that indirect sunlight is actually the best. It's certainly how it's practiced.
אמר רב אמי בר שמואל בכולן אין בודקין אותן אלא בין חמה
לצל. Amar Rav Ami bar Shmuel bekullan ein bodkin otan ela bein
hamma latsel. And here it says it succinctly exactly that way that
this is the ideal. All of these should only be checked between
direct sunlight and shade; don't be totally in shade, don't be in
direct sunlight, be in indirect sunlight. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה בחמה ובצל ידו. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha behamma
uvetzel yado. You can use, you can do it in outside in
the direct sunlight but use your hand to give you some shade,
so put one hand on top of it. And this produces again
רש"י Rashi reads this as that this is acceptable but it actually
seems that this is the ideal. Okay and now we finally wrap
up the משנה Mishna about colors. Yeah. Yeah. Fascinating. So meaning and
less and therefore less red? Very interesting. Right, right, that's fascinating point
similar to the issue of the candlelight. So is the issue of
indirect sunlight just that it's not so harsh so it doesn't strain
your eyes or is the issue that it actually brings out a
different spectrum? Yeah I don't know that's an excellent point. Okay so
let's wrap up the פרק. perek. וכמזוג שני חלקים Ukhemazug shenei chalakim
so this is finally we get to the issue about the color
of wine, like wine that is this from the Sharon Valley, two
parts wine, one part or excuse me two parts water, one part
wine. דתניא השרוני נידון ככרמלי חי De-tanya Hasharoni nidon ke-Charmeli chai that
the Sharon wine, mixed Sharon wine has the same color for these
purposes as raw unmixed wine from the כרמל. Carmel. ולא מזוג חדש
ולא ישן Velo mazug chadash velo yashan and not wine should not
be fresh just freshly squeezed and not particularly old. אמר רב יוסף
בר אבדומי וכולן אין בודקין אותן אלא בכוס טבריא. Amar Rav Yosef
bar Avdumi vekullan ein bodkin otan ela bekos Tverya. All of these
you should only check when you're looking at the wine color if
it's in a Tiberian glass; presumably obviously also what the container is
will affect what the color of the wine is. פשוט, Pashut, excuse
me, a simple Tiberian glass. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
אמר אביי שכל העולם כולו מחזיק לוג עושין אותו מנה. Amar Abaye
shekol ha'olam kulo machzik log osin oto mane. Normal cups if you
have something that holds whatever a gallon you make it out of
whatever it is a pound of copper whatever it's made of a
pound of glass and שני לוגין עושין אותו ממאתים shenei login osin
oto mimatayim two gallons you make it out of two pounds. כוס
טבריא פשוט Kos Tverya pashut a simple Tiberian cup אפילו מחזיק שני
לוגין afilu machzik shenei login even if it's very large to hold
two לוג, log, עושין אותו ממנה. osin oto mimane. You make it
only out of the same amount out of one whatever pound of
a material of glass. So therefore the point being as it says
איידי דקליש Aidi dekallish and therefore since the glass is very thin
ידיע ביה טפי Yedei bei tefei you can have a you see
the color of what it holds better. So the basic answer being
that it's made out of a thin glass and therefore you can
see the color better. הדרן עלך כל היד Hadran alach Kol Hayad
that was the end of that פרק perek and of course the
end of that פרק perek as you saw was really critical in
terms of questions about defining what is blood of a נדה, Nidda,
uterine blood and the colors and also the very practice of בדיקה.
We learned about the types of cloth and about asking שאלות and
that whole dynamic between the rabbi and the women who bring the
questions and ruling for yourselves and the questions here also about the
light in which you look at it. And now we turn to
a פרק perek that takes us a little bit away directly from
נדה, Nidda, sort of a certainly obviously about that as well but
focuses on the טומאת יולדת. tumas yoledes. A woman who gives birth
has טומאת הנדה tumas hanidda for a same type of טומאה; tumah;
if it's a boy for a week, if it's a girl for
two weeks and then comes a period of thirty-three or sixty-six days
respectively if that even if she sees blood it's not a problem.
That's called the דמי טוהר demei tohar and and so and the
other important point is that this is even, this is not a
Cesarean section I should mention as we'll see later, it's a vaginal
birth and all but also it is even for a miscarriage. As
long as the baby is fetus is developed forty days then even
if it is a, then even for a miscarriage the woman is
טמאה יולדת. tmeya yoledes. The exception to however are if not if
it's not yet fully developed or if it is if it's deformed
and not naturally developed and it's not considered to have human form.
So that is what we're going to be looking at a lot
here is the issue of the טומאת יולדת. tumas yoledes. Don't worry,
there's plenty of נדה Niddah in מסכת נדה. Maseches Niddah. Okay, so
now I don't know, we can we can worry about that. But
okay, let's take a look. Let's first get through some of this
פרק Perek and then we could take a step back and try
to frame that. Okay so, המפלת חתיכה. Hamapeles Chatichah. So a woman
that has a miscarriage, I mean it's used the phrase miscarriage, but
for the context, you know, it means also just like מפיל, Mapil,
falls out or causes to to be discharged from her body. Because
again, the reason here it's using the phrase המפלת Hamapeles is I
believe just partially the ongoing question is always: should we consider this
a miscarriage or something, you know, that was is not a fetus
and not to be concerned about? So a woman who discharges a
little, a chunk, some type of a thing. אם יש עמה דם
טמאה. Im yesh imah dam temeiah. It comes out with blood then
fine, the blood makes her a נדה. Niddah. And the general rule
as we said is that even if a woman sees מחמת אונס,
machmas ones, as a result of something else, if it's this if
it's the uterine if it's blood from the uterine lining, she is
a נדה. Niddah. ואם לאו טהורה, Ve-im lav tehorah, but if there's
no blood with it she's טהורה tehorah because this little chunk does
not make her a נדה. Niddah. רבי יהודה אומר בין כך ובין
כך טמאה, Rabbi Yehudah omer bein kach u-vein kach temeiah, either way
she is טמאה temeiah and we will see why that'll be the
focus of the גמרא, why. המפלת, Hamapeles, now we get to the
question about so that's one question of that there's that thing does
not seem to be a fetus, there's no blood, could there be
a reason for the woman to still be a נדה? Niddah? It
would not seem to be. Now we get to the question about
what would constitute a fetus in order to make the woman טמאה
לידה. temeiah leidah. So, המפלת כמין קליפה, Hamapeles k’min klipah, if it
looks like some type of a shell that came out of her,
כמין שעורה, k’min se’orah, a hair, I'm sorry, כמין שעורה, k’min se’orah,
a barley bean, excuse me, כמין שערה k’min searah was right the
first time, שערה, searah, I'm reading with the tiny text here, a
hair, כמין עפר, k’min afar, looks like dirt, dust, כמין יבחושים k’min
yavchushim or like gnat, אדומים, adumim, red, then how do you know?
Maybe it is there's no question here such tiny little fragments of
things, it's certainly not a fetus. Question is, maybe it's dried up
blood. So what do you do? הטילו למים, Hatilu le-mayim, put it
in water. אם נמוחו טמאה, Im nimochu temeiah, if it dissolves, טמאה
temeiah because it's dried up blood, presumably it also had a reddish
color. ואם לאו טהורה, Ve-im lav tehorah, if it doesn't dissolve then
it's not dried up blood, it's some of something else and she's
not נדה. Niddah. Now, המפלת כמין דגים חגבים שקצים ורמשים, Hamapeles k’min
dagim chagavim shekatzim u-remasim, let's say we're talking about something more substantial,
it looks like a real, you know, thing there, something that once
had some maybe life in it, who knows? But it doesn't look
human. It looks like fish or grasshoppers or, you know, a rodent,
other types of things. So אם יש עמהם דם טמאה, Im yesh
imahem dam temeiah, so if there's blood then she's a נדה. Niddah.
ואם לאו טהורה, Ve-im lav tehorah, if not she's טהורה. tehorah. It
is not considered a miscarriage, a fetus. המפלת מין בהמה חיה ועוף,
Hamapeles min behemah chayah va-of, however, if it looks like some type
of an animal or bird, בין טמא בין טהור, Bein tamei bein
tahor, whether a kosher or not kosher bird or animal, doesn't matter,
looks but looks of one of those, then she then that does
have the status of a fetus. And therefore, now what type is
it, male or female? Because there's a difference as we said. So
אם זכר תשב לזכר, Im zachar teshev le-zachar, so you look, if
you can actually see male genitalia, תשב לזכר, teshev le-zachar, then it's
a male birth or miscarriage of a male, and it's 7 טמאה
temeiah days and 33 טהורה tehorah days. ואם נקבה תשב לנקבה, Ve-im
nekeivah teshev le-nekeivah, and if you see that it's a female, then
it's 14 and 66. ואם אינו ידוע תשב לזכר ולנקבה, Ve-im eino
yadua teshev le-zachar u-le-nekeivah, דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, she has
to do it male and female, which means she's strict both ways.
14 טמאה temeiah days and only 33 clean days. Now it's not
really 33 because of those 33, the first seven she's been טמאה.
temeiah. So it really works out to be 14 טמאה temeiah days
and then what is it, 26 clean days? That's how you're strict
both ways if you don't know male or female. דברי רבי מאיר,
Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. וחכמים אומרים
כל שאין בו מצורת אדם אינו ולד, Va-Chachamim omrim kol she-ein bo
mi-tzuras adam eino valad, I'm sorry, if it does not have a
human appearance even if it looks like these animals, it is not
considered to be a fetus and she is not a יולדת. yoledet.
She does not have the טומאה tumah of of a woman who
has given childbirth or miscarriage. I don't know, we will no, we're
not going to get to that today. Okay, we're quite behind. So
let's hold off questions. So let's take a look at the גמרא
now. So the first focus, most of this focus as you see
is on what constitutes a fetus for these הלכות, halachos, but the
first question is that when it was clearly when it was just
a chunk and there was no blood, then we have רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah saying טמא. tamei. Why should that be? So let's look
at the גמרא. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל לא טימא רבי יהודה
אלא בחתיכה של ארבעה מיני דמים אבל של שאר מיני דמים טהורה.
Amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel lo timah Rabbi Yehudah ela b’chatichah shel
arba’ah minei damim aval shel shear minei damim tehorah. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah only said this when it had one of the red
appearances, the four colors of red. Then basically he's assuming that even
though it's a chunk, really it's it is a type of blood.
And for whatever reason I don't know you can't do the dissolve
test, maybe it's too thick or too hardened, but he's still going
to be concerned that it's blood. And the חכמים *Chachamim* say no,
even if it looks red, it's not blood. So that's the issue,
is just if the chunk is blood. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר
*Rabbi Yochanan amar* no, של ארבעה מיני דמים דברי הכל טמאה teme'ah
*shel arbaah minei damim divrei hakol tmeia*. If it looks those four
colors of red then everybody would say it's dried blood. Again, interesting
why no discussion of the dissolve test. של שאר מיני דמים דברי
הכל טהורה tehora. *shel shaar minei damim divrei hakol tehora*. If it
looks like the acceptable colors, green and yellow and who knows what,
then everybody would agree it's not a problem. So okay, where do
they debate? לא נחלקו אלא שהפילה ובין ידעה מה הפילה *lo necheleku
ela shehepila uvein yadea ma hepila*. The whole issue is that he
she did not, she doesn't see what she discharged, it got lost.
רבי יהודה סבר אזיל בתר רוב חתיכות *Rabbi Yehuda savar azil batar
rov chatichot*, רוב חתיכות של ארבעה מיני דמים הויין *rov chatichot shel
arbaah minei damim havyan*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says go by most
discharges that come from a woman, the vaginal discharges, which are the
red color, and therefore we have to assume that that was the
story here. ורבנן סברי לא אמרינן רוב חתיכות של ארבעה מיני דמים
*veRabanan savri lo amrinan rov chatichot shel arbaah minei damim*. We don't
say that, either they disagree with the facts or they actually say
she has a חזקת טהרה *chezkat tahara*, she has a status of
being טהור tahor *tahor*, and we're not going to change that based
on רוב *rov*. Okay, so according to them the whole issue, no
questions, according to them the whole issue is about whether about what
we can that if it is that if it is red, it's
definitely a problem and the whole question is what can we assume
if we don't know. So גמרא *Gemara* says איני *eini*, can that
really be true, either of these ways of framing the issue that
basically if it's red it's a problem? והא כי אתא רב אושעיא
מנהרדעא אתא ואייתי מתניתא בידיה *veha ki ata Rav Oshaya minehardea ata
veaiti matnita bideih*, when רב אושעיא *Rav Oshaya* came from מנהרדעא *Nehardea*,
he had a ברייתא braita *braita* that he came and he reported
on, that he had there was a tradition there of a particular
ברייתא braita *braita*, and here's the ברייתא braita *braita*. המפלת חתיכה hamapeles
chaticha אדומה *hamapelet chaticha aduma*, if a woman discharges some type of
a red chunk, שחורה ירוקה ולבנה *shchora yeruka ulvana*, or black, now
or green and or what or green, yellow, or white. So what's
the story? So those are bad colors and good colors in terms
of blood. אם יש עמה דם טמאה ואם לאו טהורה im yesh
ima dam tmeia veim lav tehora. *im yesh ima dam tmeia veim
lav tehora*. The חכמים *Chachamim* say I really don't care about the
color of the of the chunk, I care is that is not
considered blood, if there's blood with it she's טמאה tmeia. *tmeia*, if
there's no blood with it she's טהורה tehora. *tehora*. רבי יהודה אומר
בין כך ובין כך טמאה tmeia. *Rabbi Yehuda omer bein kach uvein
kach tmeia*, and he's strict either way, whether it's a problematic color
or even not a problematic color, she is טמאה tmeiah *tmeia*. So
that's really surprising, what's that based on? So anyway before the גמרא
*Gemara* gets to analyzing that, it first points out that this that
this contradicts both both positions we said before. תיובתא דשמואל בחדא ודרבי
יוחנן בתרתי *tiyuvta d'Shmuel bechada ve'deRabbi Yochanan betartei*. So this contradicts one
point of שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* and two points of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*. דשמואל בחדא *deShmuel bechada*, one point of שמואל *Shmuel*, דאמר שמואל
לא טימא רבי יהודה אלא בחתיכה של ארבעה מיני דמים *de'amar Shmuel
lo timmei Rabbi Yehuda ela bechaticha shel arbaah minei damim*, that he
says that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s problem was only if it looked
red. והא קתני *veha katani*, and this ברייתא braisa *braita* says ירוקה
ולבנה *yeruka ulvana*, gives an example of green or yellow, ופליג upalig,
רבי יהודה *uplig Rabbi Yehuda*, and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* disagrees and
says that it's still טמאה tmeiah, *tmeia*. וכי תימא כי פליג רבי
יהודה אאדומה ושחורה *vechi teima ki plig Rabbi Yehuda a'aduma u'shchora*, maybe
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s only saying no in the case of red
and black I'll say טמאה tmeiah *tmeia*, not in the case of
green and white. וירוקה ולבנה לא *veyeruka ulvana lo*. We started with
describing a case of green and white, but I wouldn't go so
far as to say that that case was טמאה *tmeia*. So no,
you can't say that. אלא ירוקה ולבנה למאן קתני לה *ela yeruka
ulvana leman katani la*? So why did the ברייתא braisa *braita* even
mention green and white if he's not ruling on that? אילימא לרבנן
eilima lerabanan, *eileima leRabanan*, maybe to tell you that the rabbis' ruling
applies even to green and white? You don't need to say that.
השתא אדומה ושחורה מטהרי רבנן *hashta aduma u'shchora metaheri Rabanan*, if they
say black or red is okay, ירוקה ולבנה מיבעיא yeruka ulevana mibaya?
*yeruka ulvana mibaya*? Is there any question that they would say green
and white is okay? So obviously if it's using the example of
green and white, it's to tell you that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
that says that
says טמאה *tmeia* would say it
even in the case of green and white. So therefore we have
contradicted שמואל *Shmuel* that limits רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* to the case
of red. אלא לאו ela lav. לרבי יהודה ופליג *ela lav leRabbi
Yehuda uplig*, it's saying it according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and
he argues and even the case of green and white he says
is טמאה *tmeia*. ותו ודרבי יוחנן דאמר של ארבעה מיני דמים דברי
הכל טמאה *vetu u'deRabbi Yochanan de'amar shel arbaah minei
damim divrei hakol tmeia*. Now רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* remember said that
red even the rabbis would agree. Well that's patently wrong according to
this ברייתא *braita*. והא קתני אדומה ושחורה *veha katani aduma u'shchora*, it
says starts with the case of red and black, ופליגי upligi, רבנן
*upligi Rabanan*, and the rabbis say that even those cases are טהור
*tahor*. וכי תימא כי פליגי רבנן אירוקה ולבנה *vechi teima ki pligi
Rabanan ayruka ulvana*, maybe the rabbis are only saying it's okay by
the green and white case, אבל אדומה ושחורה לא *aval aduma u'shchora
lo*, but by the red and the black of that ברייתא *braita*
they actually would agree that that is a problem. You can't say
that. אלא אדומה ושחורה למאן קתני לה *ela aduma u'shchora leman katani
la*? Then why did he even mention the case of red and
black? אילימא לרבי יהודה *eileima leRabbi Yehuda*, maybe to tell you that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* if it's for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s sake,
no, השתא ירוקה ולבנה מטמא *hashta yeruka ulvana metamei*, if he's saying
the case of green and white רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says green
and white is טמאה *tmeia*, so if that's true, אדומה ושחורה מיבעיא
*aduma u'shchora mibaya*? It goes without saying that the case of black
and red would be would be טמאה *tmeia*. So why did it
bother giving the case of black and red? To tell you אלא
לאו רבנן *ela lav Rabanan*, that even the rabbis say that black
and red is okay, for the rabbis even black and red is
okay, ופליגי *upligi*, and they argue. So that was you know it
was basically the short version of that was, look, it's explicit that
It was with all different colors and it says that the Rabbis
always say it's okay and רב יהודה Reb Yehuda says it's always
no good. So you can't try to say that the colors matter
and that that's what the debate is limited to or that's the
basis of the debate or anything. Clearly the Rabbis are fine with
red color and clearly רב יהודה'ס Reb Yehuda's issue is different than
color. So then what is it really based on? אלא אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק ela amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak באפשר לפתיחת
הקבר בלא דם קמיפלגי.
be-efshar le-phtichat ha-kever
be-lo dam ka-miflagi. The question is, can there be, I'll translate it
literally, an opening of the grave without blood? Now here what is
the קבר, kever, is a grave. So if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, פתיחת הקבר phtichat ha-kever that's about ten lines
before the lines get wide, before the bottom, I guess twelve lines,
הרחם, ha-rechem, the womb. Now it's quite interesting and disturbing, you know,
that the womb here is being dis- called the קבר. kever. I
mean until now we've had רחם rechem which obviously you know רחמים
rachamim obviously has very positive connotations, מקור, makor, you know source, spring,
source of life. Okay, we've once we had this בית bayit metaphor,
maybe it was also called חדר cheder which is okay, at least
relatively neutral. But קבר kever is obviously very disturbing. But there's a
reason why it's being called קבר kever here. First thank you, because
here we are deal- I know, thank you, because here we are
dealing with
a
case of miscarriage. And so here it actually
was a קבר, kever, actually the child actually did die. Although it's
actually not true because in the case of the משנה Mishnah
it's
just a little chunk, but we
will see in a minute that we, so who knows, it might
not even have been a fetus, but we'll see in a minute
that more explicit cases of
a miscarriage and
of a fetus. But what is disturbing is that later פוסקים, Poskim,
you know, just using גמרא
terminology talk about this
in a
quest- in questions of normal issues in which things come out of-
you know, gynecological exams and other types of issues and they use
the same phrase of פתיחת הקבר בלא דם phtichat ha-kever be-lo dam
and קבר kever becomes used to refer to the
womb even in
a case not relating to miscarriage. So it's important to note that
in the גמרא'ס Gemara's case the reason for this choice was specifically
that all these cases deal with, deal with something being expelled that
is not, that you know, not birth and it's, most of these
cases are cases of miscarriage. So, so that's the issue. So why
does רב יהודה Reb Yehuda so א, alef, the Rabbis, they're not
bothered
with a red color, they say it isn't blood, it's something else,
it's some chunk, but it's not blood. Again I don't know why
we don't do the dissolving test, maybe it's too hard. And רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda says I don't care about the color and it's
always טמא tamei because I say whenever something is being discharged from
the woman's womb, there will be some blood that will come with
it. And even if it's not due to menstruation as we said
before, the status of נדה niddah as long as it's the- even
if it's because of אונס, ones, the woman is still going to
be טמאה even if- as long as it is for some reason
it's causing some of the menstrual lining to come off. So that
is the debate. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי u-v'p'lugta d'hanei Tannai and it follows
the debate of the- of the following תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא di-tanya it
was taught in the ברייתא, קשתה שניים ולשלישי הפילה kashta shnayim u-lishlishi
hepila ואינו יודע מה הפילה. ve-eino yode'a mah hepila. So a woman
had contractions, you know, birth pains for two days and she was
bleeding during those two days. To remind you, the הלכה halacha is
is that if a woman bleeds during her זבה zava period, during
the eleven days after the seven days of
the נדה niddah period,
if a woman bleeds during that
period and she would be a
זבה, zava, the one exception to the rule that it does not
matter if it's due to some other factor is the issue
of childbirth
and blood of a זבה. zava. So a
woman could be a נדה niddah during childbirth, which is what our
משנה Mishnah was talking about, but
by a זבה, zava, if she is bleeding during the זבה zava
period and it is coming with birth pains and these birth pains
continue all the way up to the actual birth itself, then that
blood is not material, that is not the זבה zava blood. So
here is the scenario. Now to be a full זבה, zava, זבה
גדולה,
zava
gedola,
a set requiring
several- seven clean days, requires three consistent days of bleeding.
So this woman bled for two days with the birth pains and
on the third day she had birth pains as well and she
bled. So if it be a childbirth,
she wouldn't be a זבה, zava, because if it wouldn't be a
childbirth,
she would be a זבה. zava. Then what happens? Then she miscarried.
Now miscarriage
also
would make her a non-זבה zava because it was still the fetus
and whatever that was causing it up to the point that it
actually came out. So and on the third day she miscarried. Now
here's the kicker though, ואינו יודע מה הפילה. ve-eino yode'a mah hepila.
She doesn't know, you know, what the- what the fetus looked like,
you know, in our משנה Mishnah we see that if
it doesn't have a human
appearance and certainly if it appears as other things, it would not
be considered to
be a
birth. So here's the issue. What is her status?
If it was considered הלכתית halachicly a fetus,
then
she
is a יולדת yoledet because she had a- you
know, she miscarried a fetus, but she's not a זבה zava because
since she
is a יולדת, yoledet, it's
considered a birth, that means that the bleeding is not material and
she's not a זבה. zava. If it
wasn't a miscarriage, then- because it wasn't a fetus, then she
is a
זבה. zava. So that- and therefore that is the question. הרי זו
ספק לידה ספק זיבה. harei zu sefek leida sefek ziva. So she's
a questionable יולדת, yoledet, a questionable זבה. zava. It's possible that it's
also possible that she's neither because I actually had simplified the case
before, I said she bled on the third day, but actually she
doesn't know. Maybe blood came out with this fetus, maybe it
didn't. So there's a possibility she's neither. Maybe it doesn't have
a status of a fetus and maybe there was no blood that
came out with it and she's neither a זבה
zava
nor
a יולדת. yoledes. So therefore so that's the question. So what do
you do in that case? מביאה קרבן ואינו נאכל. mevia korban ve'eino
ne'echal. She has to
bring a קרבן korban because either as a if as
a
זבה zava or a יולדת yoledes she
would require a קרבן, korban, but you can't eat it because she
might have been neither. She doesn't have to bring two קרבנות korbanos
because she can't be both, she's either one or the other. רבי
יהושע אומר מביאה קרבן ונאכל. Rabbi Yehoshua omer mevia korban vene'echal. No
actually she definitely
has to bring
a
קרבן korban and it can be eaten. Why? Maybe she's neither a
זבה zava nor a יולדת? yoledes? No, שאי אפשר
לפתיחת הקבר
בלא דם. she'ee efshar lipetichat hakever belo dam.
Here clearly it's a case of miscarriage. שאי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר
בלא דם. she'ee efshar lipetichat hakever belo dam. You cannot have the
opening of the of the grave without blood and therefore definitely blood
came out. So here you see that they're explicitly debating if you
do not see blood you have to assume blood in this type
of a case of a miscarriage. לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way
of saying this. אמרו ליה. amru lei. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. So this is really going
to be pretty
much a repeat of what we said before except it's not going
to have רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's position about that you know that
the case where you don't know what had happened. So let's
take a look, this should go pretty quickly. לא תימא רב יהודה
אלא בחתיכה של ארבעה מיני דמים. lo teima Rav Yehuda ela bechaticha
shel arba'ah minei damim. So in the name of שמואל says that
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda only says his ruling when it was had
the appearance of red. אבל שאר מיני דמים טהורה. aval she'ar minei
damim tehora. But if the chunk did not have a red look
he would say it's טהורה. tehorah. איני והא כי אתא רב הושעיא
מנהרדעא אתא ואייתי מתניתא בידיה. eini veha ki ata Rav Oshaya minehardea
ata veaiti matnita bidei. When רב הושעיא Rav Oshaya came from נהרדעא
Nehardea he brought the ברייתא with the following ברייתא with him. המפלת
חתיכה אדומה ושחורה ירוקה ולבנה. hamapelet chaticha aduma ushchora yeruka ulevana. So
if a woman sort of
discharges a red, black, yellow, green, or
white type of a chunk. אם
יש עמה דם טמאה ואם לאו טהורה. v'im lav tehorah The only
thing that matters is whether there's blood, if there's no blood it's
טהורה. tehorah. רב יהודה אומר בין כך ובין כך טמאה. Rav Yehuda
omer bein kach uvein kach tmeia. Either way she is טמאה. Why?
טמאה. So even if it is a non-problematic color. קתני אדומה ושחורה
ירוקה ולבנה. katani aduma ushchora yeruka ulevana. So we have mentioned all
four of these colors. ופליגי, and they argue. ופליגי רב יהודה upligi
Rav Yehuda argues even with a except even
with a green or yellow color it's not a
problem, I mean it
is a problem. וכי תימא כי פליג רב יהודה אדומה ושחורה. vechi
teima ki palig Rav Yehuda aduma ushchora. Maybe he only says the
red and black
is a problem.
אבל ירוקה ולבנה לא. aval yeruka ulevana lo. But the yellow, green,
the white, no. וירוקה ולבנה מאן קתני לה? veyeruka ulevana man katani
la? Then why was it bothered to have mentioned the case of
the green, yellow, or the white if
it's not a
problem? אילימא לרבנן, if it's to tell you that the Rabbis who
say it's טהור say
even in a yellow or white case. ירוקה
ולבנה ואילימא לרבנן והשתא אדומה ושחורה קמטהרי רבנן. yeruka ulevana ve'eilima lerabanan
vehashta aduma ushchora kametahari rabanan. If they say that even red and
black is okay, ירוקה ולבנה מיבעיא? Any question that the yellow and
the white would be okay? אלא לאו. So it tells you a
yellow
and a white chunk in this ברייתא and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda.
says טמא. tamei. It is clear that רב יהודה'ס Rav Yehuda's ruling
is even in that case. אלא לאו לרב יהודה, ela lav leRav
Yehuda, even it said for the sake of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda
ופליג, רב יהודה says even yellow
and white is a problem. Why? Because it is not about the
color being this thing being blood, it is about what comes out
with it. Hold on just one second. I have to rearrange myself.
One more second. Okay, I'm back. So really that was
just a repeat of what we had been before but without the
רבי יוחנן and we now what we have this concept of שאי
אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא
דם, she'ee efshar lipetichat hakever belo dam, which is a critical concept
because as I said this gets applied to not only cases of
miscarriage but other cases as well and in particular to cases of
gynecological exams which I'll discuss in a minute. Let's first see
a little bit more גמרא. Where are we? אלא אמר רבי יוחנן.
ela amar Rabbi Yochanan. So it's not based on the color of
the piece, what's it based on? שאי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם.
she'ee efshar lipetichat hakever belo dam. That's the question about can it
open without blood coming out. וכמיפלגי בפלוגתא דהני תנאי, uchmipalgi beflugta dehanei
tanai, and it's the same as the debate of these תנאים. tannaim.
So you see this is all a repeat, let's speed up a
little bit. דתניא. detanya. המקשה
שנים ולשלישי
הפילה, hamaksha shnayim velishlishi hepila, a woman has birth pain for two
days and with blood, third day she miscarries doesn't know if there's
blood with it. ואינה יודעת מה הפילה. ve'eina yoda'at ma hepila. She
doesn't even know the nature of the miscarriage. הרי זו ספק. harei
zu safek. Again, if it was considered a birth, it was considered
a fetus, halakhically then
the
blood does not
make her a
זבה *zavah*. If
it is not
considered a
יולדת *yoledes*, if it is
not a fetus, then
the
blood makes her a זבה *zavah*. So she is either זבה
*zavah* or a
יולדת *yoledes* and of course it might be neither because maybe no
blood came out on the third day. So what is the halakha?
מביאה קרבן ואינו נאכל *mevia korban ve-eino ne'echal*, she brings a sacrifice
but it is not eaten. רבי יהושע אומר מביאה קרבן ונאכל *Rabbi
Yehoshua omer mevia korban ve-ne'echal*, no, she is definitely
either a
יולדת *yoledes* or a זבה *zavah* because some definitely some blood came
out on the third day, so she has to be one. Because
אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם *ee efshar le-pesichas hakever belo dam*,
it is impossible for the womb to open without blood. So the
distinction here is is that you know this גמרא *Gemara* is all
talking about when something is discharged from
the uterus commonly and particularly case about a miscarriage where there is
obviously some you know some sort of serious type of pain some
sort of pressure going on
inside. The נודע ביהודה *Noda Bi-Yehudah* however applies this even to a
case where there is an opening of the uterus coming
from the outside, some type of a
gynecological exam, an instrument is stuck in through the cervix and certainly
you know up into the up through the os from
the cervix to the opening of the uterus, we would say that
אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם *ee efshar le-pesichas hakever belo dam*
and the woman is נדה
*niddah*, which is a huge חידוש *chiddush* applying it in the other
direction. רב משה פיינשטיין *Rav Moshe Feinstein* pretty much spends outside years
arguing on the נודע ביהודה *Noda Bi-Yehudah* pretty much makes it moot
because based on his argument says that that would only be true
if the thing being inserted was I think three quarters of an
inch or larger. And now and nowadays certainly I don't think if
there's doctors in the room but I think it's almost never that
there's any medical instrument that is inserted under normal gynecological types of
procedures and exams that is that thick. So he pretty much makes
the נודע ביהודה *Noda Bi-Yehudah* moot. But that becomes a very important
discussion around this גמרא *Gemara*. So let's no because it's not oh
if if the gynecological exam causes scraping or irritation or whatever vaginal
bleeding then it's certainly דם מכה *dam makka*. But what what the
נודע ביהודה *Noda Bi-Yehudah* says is it doesn't matter. Something it causes
there's a פתיחה *pesicha*, there's something that's inserted in and therefore some
type of דם *dam* which is not דם מכה *dam makka* like
the גמרא *Gemara* here says it's not דם מכה *dam makka*, it's
blood of the uterine lining will come off and that will make
her a and that will make her
a נדה *niddah*. So that's the assumption here is it's not דם
מכה *dam makka*, here the assumption
is just that it is
a what do you call it? That this experience
this event causes the uterine lining to come off, some of the
uterine lining to come
off. Okay, so that
is a very critical גמרא *Gemara*. Now let's just see
from another ברייתא *braita* that
just gives a couple more clarifications to this to this ברייתא *braita*
משנה *Mishnah*. So תנו רבנן *Tanu
rabbanan*, we learned a ברייתא *braita*. המפלת חתיכה hamapeles chaticha *Hamapeles chaticha*,
so again this woman
who has this chunk that is
discharged, סומכוס Sumchus אומר משום רבי מאיר *Sumchos omer mishum Rabbi Meir*,
so סומכוס Sumchus *Sumchos* says in the name of רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, וכן היה רבי שמעון בן ננס אומר כדבריו *vechen haya Rabbi
Shimon ben Nanas omer kidvarav*, רבי שמעון בן ננס *Rabbi Shimon ben
Nanas*
also said the same. קורעה kora *kor'ah*, you cut it open. אם
יש דם בתוכה *Im yesh dam betochah*, and now the question is
is this this chunk actually soaked in blood and that's the problem?
So that's what we say now.
You know what? Tear it open. אם יש דם בתוכה *Im yesh
dam betochah*, if there's some blood inside of it, so it's more
like a sac of something that contains some liquid, if there is
blood inside of it then then טמאה *teme'ah*, she's tamei, and if
not טהורה *tehorah*. The fact that it was in the sac doesn't
matter, it's blood coming out. כרבנן *Ke-rabbanan*, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
that's like the Rabbis that don't believe in this פתיחת הקבר *pesichas
hakever* concern. עדיפא מרבנן *Adifa me-rabbanan*, but עדיפא *adifa* here doesn't mean
better, it means like stricter,
stronger than the Rabbis. The Rabbis were never concerned about this
being blood, but he is concerned that if it contains blood it
is a problem. ואינו סבירא ליה כרבנן *ve-ino sevira lei ke-rabbanan*, like
the Rabbis, דאמרי אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם *d'amri ee efshar
le-pesichas hakever belo dam*, that it is possible that the womb opens
without blood so if we don't see blood we don't have to
be concerned about it. ועדיפא מרבנן *Ve-adifa me-rabbanan*, but stricter, דאינהו סברי
אימא אינא ובחתיכה לא *d'inhu savri imma ina u-ve-chaticha lo*. Only if
blood is on the outside but not on the inside. This is
going to be a focus of the גמרא *Gemara*, the story of
blood that comes out but is not touching the vaginal canal. So
they say it is only on the outside but not on the
inside. Sorry, just hold on, let me read it to myself. Where
are we? Sorry. וסומכוס סבר אפילו בתוכה *Ve-Sumchos savar afilu betochah*, even
on the inside. ותני אידא v'sani ida ובתר הכי ברייתא v'basar hachi
braisa המפלת חתיכה ורבי עקיבא אומר v'Rabbi Akiva omer says קורעה kora
tear it open. אם תוכו מאדים im tocho ma'adim if inside is
red, reddish טמאה she's טמאה, ואם לאו טהורה v'im lav tehorah and
if not she's טהורה. כסומכוס k'Sumchus like סומכוס Sumchus that we don't
say automatically blood came out and but and like סומכוס Sumchus that
it matters what's on the inside and even stricter than סומכוס because
obviously here it doesn't have to be blood it just has to
be red. ותני אידא and there's a third ברייתא המפלת
חתיכה again if a chunk comes out רבי בנימין אומר Rabbi Binyamin
omer says קורעה kora tear it open. אם יש בה עצם im
yesh bah etzem אם אמו טמאה לידה. im imo tmeiah leidah. Let's
not worry about blood, tear it open if
there's
a
bone in it, עצם, etzem, it's not blood coming out it's a
fetus and then the mother is טמאה לידה.
tmeiah leidah.
So you don't really
need a lot of comments on that, that's really taking us in
another direction, a
concern
about a fetus not a concern about blood.
Sorry, having a lot of speaker
issues now. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa ודווקא חתיכה לבנה v'davka
chaticha levana that's only if it's not red but white, whitish you
know clearish whitish then we can say actually it's a fetus. וכן
כי אתא זוגא
דחדיב v'chen ki ata zuga d'Chadyav and similarly
when a pair of scholars came
from this
place חדיב Chadyav ואתו ואייתו
מתניתא בידייהו v'aso v'aysu masnisa b'yadayhu they came and
brought
a
ברייתא in their hands המפלת חתיכה לבנה hamapeles chaticha levana if
somebody has a
discharge of a white chunk קורעה
tear it open אם יש בה עצם אמו טמאה לידה im yesh
bah etzem imo tmeiah leidah
and if there's a bone the mother is טמאה לידה. tmeiah leidah.
So there's two concerns: is it possibly blood, it depends on whether
there's red, red inside and so on, blood inside it, or is
it possibly the case of a miscarriage and nobody really is debating
the second issue, the concern about the fetus, but the issue about
the blood was the big question about whether it really matters what's
inside if the blood was not on the outside. So let's just
finish this up. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai המפלת חתיכה קורעה hamapeles chaticha
kora אם יש בה דם אגור טמאה. im yesh bah dam agur
tmeiah. So you open up this tear it open, Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai saying if you open up this chunk and if there is
a lot of blood, blood collected then she is טמאה ואם לאו
טהורה and if not she is טהורה. כסומכוס k'Sumchus like סומכוס that
don't automatically say blood came out, but דהקילו מכולהו d'hikilu mikulhu more
lenient than all of them. We had an opinion reddish, we had
an opinion blood, here they will not say it's a problem
unless it is a
lot of blood and
only then is
it a problem.
So we will
end with this גמרא, we will pick up on the sort of
conceptual question being
raised here about what does why should it matter if it's on
the inside
or the outside and that also has a lot of relevance in
terms of application for some contemporary issues. So that'll be it for
now. Okay see you all tomorrow. Okay everybody still there? Okay.
Yeah I'll be I'll be
there tomorrow. Okay take care. Goodbye. Good to see you kids, you
should've brought them in the picture. Poof.